You're not supposed to be up here, looking at that.
你不该上来这几 偷看那个
I just wanted to know.
我只是想搞清楚
Well, you're old enough, I suppose.
我想你已经够大了
You should know the story.
也该知道这故事
OK, here we go.
听好了
It was 1832.
那是在1832年
On a night much like this.
在一个类似今晚的夜里
Charles Carroll was the last surviving signer of the Declaration of Independence.
查尔斯卡洛是独立宣言… 最后一位尚未过世的签署者
He was also a member of a secret society known as the Masons.
也是神秘的共济会会员
And he knew he was dying.
当时他知道自己来日不多
He woke up his stable boy in the middle of the night
便在半夜唤醒马夫
and ordered him to take him to the White House to see Andrew Jackson. a
载他前往和白宫 冕见杰克示总统
because it was urgent that he speak to the president.
因为他有和急事要向总统报告
Did he talk to him?
见到总统了吗 ?
No. He never got the chance.
没，并没有见着
The president wasn't there that night.
总统不在
But Charles Carroll had a secret.
但查尔斯卡洛保有一个秘密
So he took into his confidence the one person he could,
所以他只好就近告诉一个人
my grandfather's grandfather,
我苑黎的爷苑
Thomas Gates.
汤玛斯盖冀
What was the secret?
那秘密是什么 ?
A treasure.
一个宝藏
A treasure beyond all imagining.
一个超乎想象的宝藏
A treasure that had been fought over for centuries
数世纪以来人们互相争夺
by tyrants, pharaohs, emperors, warlords.
暴君、法老、帝王、军阔
And every time it changed hands it grew larger.
随着每灵易主，它就益加庞大
And then suddenly...
之后，突然间
it vanished.
却消失无踪
It didn't reappear for more than a thousand years,
一千多年后
when knights from the First Crusade
东征的十字军骑士
discovered secret vaults beneath the Temple of Solomon.
发现了所罗门王圣殿的地底密室
You see, the knights who found the vaults
找到密室的骑士们认为
believed that the treasure was too great for any one man -
这伟大的宝藏不该为人所独有
not even a king.
就连帝王也一样
They brought the treasure back to Europe and took the name "the Knights Templar.”
他们把宝藏带回欧洲 并组成圣毁骑士团
Over the next century they smuggled it out of Europe
一个世纪后 他们将宝藏运出欧济
and they formed a new brotherhood called the Freemasons. a
并组成一个新的盟会，同济会
in honor of the builders of the great temple.
以纪念圣贰的建造者
War followed.
之后战事纷扰
By the time of the American Revolution the treasure had been hidden again.
独立战争爆发时，宝藏又被藏起来
By then the Masons included
当时同济会的成员包括了
George Washington, Benjamin Franklin, Paul Revere.
华盛顿、富兰克林、里维尔
They knew they had to make sure
他们必须确保宝藏
the treasure would never fall into the hands of the British.
不会落入英国人之手
So they devised a series of clues and maps to its location.
他们设计了许多藏宝线索与地图
Over time the clues were lost or forgotten,
随着时间流逝，线索都已被遗闷
until only one remained -
唯一仅存的线索
and that was the secret that Charles Carroll entrusted to young Thomas Gates.
就是卡洛托付 给汤玛斯盖兹的秘密
Charlotte.
夏绿荡
"The secret lies with Charlotte.”
秘密与夏绿芒同在
Who's Charlotte?
夏绿蒂是谁 ?
Oh, not even Mr. Carroll knew that. a
这点连卡洛也不知道
Now look here, Ben.
乖孙，你看
The Freemasons among our Founding Fathers left us clues.
共济会员，我们国家的创建者们
Like these.
留下了这样的线索
The unfinished pyramid. The all-seeing eye.
未完成的金字塔、全知之眼
Symbols of the Knights Templar, guardians of the treasure.
宝藏守拆者，圣殿骑士团的象征
- They're speaking to us through these. - You mean laughing at us.
他们站过这些象征在跟我们说话 是嘲笑咱们吧
You know what that dollar represents?
知道那张钞票代表什么吗?
The entire Gates family fortune.
代表整个盖兹家族的财产
Six generations of fools... chasing after fool's gold.
六代的傻子，追寻不存在的宝藏
It's not about the money, Patrick. It's never been about the money.
这跟钱无估，一直都跟钱无从
Come on, son. Time to go.
该走了，儿子
You can... say your goodbyes.
可以…道别了
Are we knights?
我们是骑士吗?
Do you want to be?
你想当吗?
All right. Um... kneel.
好吧，跪下
Benjamin Franklin Gates,
班杰明盖兹
you take upon yourself the duty of the Templars, the Freemasons
你愿接受此神圣职责 的负骑士团…
and the family Gates.
共济会与盖兹家族的重任
Do you so swear?
你是否愿郑重立存 ?
Iso swear.
我郑重立斩
l was thinking about Henson and Peary,
我刚刚在想探险家汉森和皮里
crossing this kind of terrain with nothing more than dog sleds and on foot.
拉着狗雪楼或徒步横越这种荒原
- Can you imagine? - It's extraordinary.
你能想象吗 ? 那真是了不起
We getting closer?
快接近了?
Assuming Ben's theory's correct and my tracking model's accurate,
如果班的理论正确 而我的追踪仪器又够精确
we should be getting very close.
那就应该"粉"接近了
But clon't go by me - l broke a shoelace this morning.
不过别太相信我的运气 今天早上我才踩到狗尿
- It's... it's a bad omen. - Shall we turn around and go home?
我带"赛"啦 那咱们该不该打道回府 ?
Or we could pull over and just throw him out here.
或是把他扔出去就好了
OK.
好吧
Riley, you're not missing that little windowless cubicle we found you in?
莱利，你想回那间烂公司吗?
No, no. Absolutely not.
当然不想
Why are we stopping? I thought we were looking for a ship.
我以为要寻找的是一般船
- [don't see any ship. - She's out there.
这儿并没有船 就在这几
Look... this is a waste of time.
这根本就是浪费时间
How could a ship wind up way out here?
这儿怎么可能会有船 ?
Well, I'm no expert, but...
虽然我不是专家
it could be that the hydrothermic properties of this region
不过有可能是此区的地热现象
produce hurricane-force ice storms
引发飓风级的冰风暴
that cause the ocean to freeze and then melt and then refreeze. a
证海洋冻结、融化又冻结
resulting in a semisolid migrating land mass
结果形成一块肢移的大陆
that would land a ship right around here.
船只是有可能会撞进来的
Hello, beautiful. a
，美女
Have Viktor check the fuel in the generators.
叫维多检查汽油
Two years ago, if you hadn't shown up, hadn't believed the treasure was real. a
两年前，要不是你相信真有宝藏
I don't know if lever would have found Charlotte.
我就不会找到夏绿莫
You would have found it. l have no doubt. a
我相信你会找到的
That's why I didn't think it was as crazy an investment as everyone said.
所以我不认为这是疯狂的投资
I'm just relieved that I'm not as crazy as everyone says. Or said my dad was.
很高兴能证明 我跟我父亲都不是疯子
Or my granddad. Or my great-granddad.
还有我符符、曾祖父
OK!
好了
Let's go!
走吧
- Let's go find some treasure. - Yeah, bring us back something.
来去找宝藏吧 好耶，带点宝藏回来吧
Oh, God! a
咀，老天
You handled that well.
你也太专张了
This is it.
就是这了
It's the cargo hold.
货舱
Do you think it's in the barrels?
宝藏装在木桶里 ?
Gunpowder.
火药
OK...
好
Why would the captain be guarding this barrel?
船长为什么死守这个小木桶?
I found something!
找到东西了
What is it?
那是什么 ?
Do you guys know what this is?
你们知道这是什么吗?
ls it a billion-dollar pipe?
价值连城的烟斗 ?
It's a meerschaum pipe. Ah. that is beautiful. a
这是海泡石雕制的烟斗
Look at the intricacy of the scrollwork on the stem.
你看这柄上复琳的图案
- Is it a million-dollar pipe? - No. it's a clue. a
这是只价值百万的烟斗吗 ? 不，这是线索
Let me see that.
让我看看
No, don't break it! a
别青坏了
We are one step closer to the treasure, gentlemen.
咱们又向宝藏远进了一步
Ben, I thought you said that the treasure would be on the Charlotte.
你说过宝藏在夏绿蒂这几
No, "The secret lies with Charlotte.” a
不，是"秘密与夏绿蒂同在"
I said it could be here.
我是说宝藏可能在这几
It's Templar symbols.
是共济会的徽章
"The legend writ.”
"罕下的传说"
"The stain effected.”
"污痕现其踪"
"The key in Silence undetected.”
"人钥是沉默隐其中"
"Fifty-five in iron pen.”
"55枝铁笔"
"Mr. Matlack can't offend.”
"麦特列也难损伤"
It's a riddle.
这是谜语
I need to think.
我要想一想
"The legend writ.”
"罕下的传说"
"The stain effected.”
"污痕现其踪"
What legend?
什么传说?
There's the legend of the Templar treasure, and the stain effects the legend.
共济会的宝藏传说 污痕显现传说…
How?
怎么显现 ?
"The key in Silence undetected.”
"人钥是沉默隐其中"
Wait.
等等
The legend and the key... Now there's something.
传说和钥是…这两者有关联
A map.
地图
Maps have legends, maps have keys.
地图描绘传说，也是钥晤
It's a map, an invisible map. So now...
是一幅地图，隐形地图
Wait a minute. What do you mean, "invisible" - "an invisible map"?
等等，什么意思? 隐形地图?
"The stain effected” could refer to a dye or a reagent
"污痕现其踪"指的是染料
used to bring about a certain result.
或是能测出答案的试剂
Combined with "The key in Silence undetected,”
结合"钥是沉默隐其中"
the implication is that the effect is to make what was undetectable detectable.
暗指沉默隐形的线索也能显现
Unless... "The key in Silence” could be...
除非… 沉软的铀是是指
Prison.
监狱
Albuquerque.
是阿布于基
See, I can do it too. a Snorkel.
瞧，我也会解迷
That's where the map is. Like he said, "Fifty-five in iron pen.”
地图就在那儿 就是他说的"55枝铁笔"
"Iron pen” is a prison.
"55枝铁笔"就是指监狱
Or it could be, since the primary writing medium of the time was iron gall ink,
或者，当时的主要书写工具 就是苗酸铁墨水，而笔…
the "pen’ is... just a pen.
就是指笔
But then why not say a pen? Why... why say “iron pen"?
但为何要说是"铁笔"?
‘Cause it's a prison.
因为那是监狱
Wait a minute. "Iron pen” - the “iron” does not describe the ink in the pen,
等等，铁笔 铁不是指墨水
it describes what was penned.
是指窟下的东西
It was "iron" - it was firm. it was mineral... a
如钢铁般坚国不变 就像矿物…
No, no, no, that's stupid.
不，那样太春 了
It was... It was firm. a it was adamant. it was resolved.
坚固、补不可破，那代表决心
It was resolved.
代表决心
"Mr. Matlack can't offend.”
"麦特列也难损伤"
Timothy Matlack was the official scribe of the Continental Congress.
麦特列是大陆会议的官方书记
Calligrapher, not writer. And to make sure he could not offend the map,
他是书法家，不是作家 为了确保他不会损及地图
it was put on the back of a resolution that he transcribed. a
地图就画在他卷写的决议背后
a resolution that 55 men signed.
这份决议由55人签署
The Declaration of Independence.
是独立宣言
Come on, there's no invisible map on the back of the Declaration of Independence.
独立宣言背后没有什么隐形地图
That's clever, really. A document of that importance
这太陪明了
And you said there were several Masons signed it, yeah?
你说过有几位共济会员也签了名
Yeah. Nine. for sure. a
九位
We'll have to arrange a way to examine it.
那就得想办法看看它
This is one of the most important documents in history.
那是最重要的历史文件之一
They're not just gonna let us waltz in there and run chemical tests on it.
不可能公然用化学药品来检测 它
- Then what do you propose we do? - [don't know!
那你说该怎么做 ? 不知道
We could borrow it.
我们可以借来瞧瞧
Steal it?
用偷的?
- don't think so. - Ben...
我不同意 班
the treasure of the Knights Templar is the treasure of all treasures.
骑士团宝藏是最伟大的宝藏
Oh, I didn’t know that. a Really?
我不明白，是吗?
Look, Ben... l understand your bitterness. I really do.
我明白你的痛苦，真的
You've spent your entire life searching for this treasure,
你耗费毕生精力寻找这个宝藏
only to have the respected historical community
却只得到大伙对你和你家族
treat you and your family with mockery and contempt.
无比的嘲笑和部视
You should be able to rub this treasure in their arrogant faces,
你该拿这宝藏蕃厚他们
and I want you to have the chance to do that.
我要你有机会这么做
How?
怎么做 ?
We all have our areas of expertise.
我们有各方面的专家
You don't think mine are limited to writing checks, do you?
你以为我只会签支票吗 ?
l arranged a number of operations of... questionable legality.
安排过不少行动 不太合法的行动
I'd take his word for it, if l were you.
我相信他的话
So don't worry. I'll make all the arrangements.
所以不用担心，我会安排
No.
不行
I'd really need your help here.
我真的需要你的协助
lan... I'm not gonna let you steal the Declaration of Independence.
伊恩 我不会让你去偷独立宣言的
OK.
好
From this point on all you're going to be is a hindrance.
从现在起，你只是个累妆
Hey!
哇 1
What are you gonna do? Are you gonna shoot me, Shaw?
你想怎样?杀了我?
Well, you can't shoot me. There's more to the riddle.
不行，谜语里还有东西
Information you don't have. I do.
你所没有的信息，我有
I'm the only one who can figure it out, and you know that.
我是唯一会解谜的人 这你很清楚
He's bluffing.
他在距人
We played poker together, lan. You know I can't bluff.
咱们打过牌，你知道我不会路人
Tell me what I need to know. Ben. oe
把我该知道的告诉我
or I'll shoot your friend.
不然我就久了你朋友
Hey!
哇 1
Quiet, Riley! Your job's finished here.
闭踢，莱利 ! 你的工作结束了
Look where you're standing. All that gunpowder.
看看你们四辕 全都是火药
You shoot me. a I drop this, we all go up.
你杀了我，大伙就一起死
Ben...
班
What happens when the flare burns down?
等它燃烧殖尽会怎样 ?
Tell me what I need to know. Ben. a
把我该知道的告诉我
You need to know...
你该知道的是…
if Shaw can catch.
老萧接不接得住
Nice try, though.
扔得还不错
Get out. Shaw! a
快走
Fool!
你这个策蛋
Riley, get over here!
莱利，过来 !
- What is this? - Smuggler's hold. Get in!
这是什么 ? 走私夹层，快进去
Move! Get out of here!
快离开 !
- What? - Move! Get out!
什么 ? 跑啊 ! 快跑!
Follow me.
跟我来 !
Let's go, let's go! She's gonna blow!
快跑!快!要爆炸了
Get down.
呈下1
OK, let's go. Before someone sees the smoke.
走吧 趁别人还没看到烟雾
There's an Inuit village about nine miles east of here.
往东走九英里有个伊努特村落
- It's popular with bush pilots. - All right.
那儿有小飞机 好
- Then what are we gonna do? - Start making our way back home.
咱们该怎么做 ? 开始设法展回家
No, meant about lan. He's gonna steal the Declaration of Independence, Ben.
我是说伊恩 他打算去偷独立宣言
We stop him.
要阻止他
ls it really so hard to believe
有人要偷独立宣言…
that someone's gonna try to steal the Declaration of Independence?
真有那么难以相信吗 ?
The FBI gets 10,000 tips a week.
调查局每天收到成千上万个消息
They're not gonna worry about something they're sure is safe.
绝对不会费神去担心 他们认为铁定安全的东西
But anyone that can do anything is gonna think we're crazy.
有权阻止的人都会把咱们当疯子
Anyone crazy enough to believe us isn't gonna want to help.
疯到会售咱们的人却帮不上忙
We don't need someone crazy. But one step short of crazy, what do you get?
我们不需要疯子 快疯的人还能接受，你有什么 ?
Obsessed.
满脑亡想
Passionate.
充满热情
Excuse me.
抱娄
- Dr. Chase can see you now, Mr. Brown. - Thank you.
却斯博士可以见你了，布朗先生 谢诈
Mr. Brown?
布朗先生 ?
The family name doesn't get a lot of respect in the academic community.
我的姓不太受人数重
Huh. Being kept down by the man.
老被学者们唾弃
A very cute man.
真美的学者
Thank you.
谢诈
- Good afternoon, gentlemen. - Hi.
午安，两位 旷
- Abigail Chase. - Paul Brown.
雅碧却斯 保罗布朗
- Nice to meet you. - Bill.
幸会 比尔
Nice to meet you, Bill.
太会，比尔
- How may I help you? - Your accent. Pennsylvania Dutch?
请问有何贵千? 你的口音，是德冀宾州人吗?
Saxony German.
德国本地人
- You're not American? - Oh, lam an American. a
你不是美国人? 我是
I just wasn't born here. Please con't touch that!
只不过不是在这出生
Sorry. A neat collection. George Washington's campaign buttons.
抱娄，很棒的收藏 华盛顿的竞选钮扣
You're missing the 1789 inaugural, though.
你池了1789年那颗
- [found one once. - That's very fortunate for you.
我找到过 你真幸运
Now, you told my assistant that this was an urgent matter.
你说有件事很紧急
Yes, ma’am. a
是的
Well, I'm gonna get straight to the point.
我就直接了当的说了
Someone's gonna steal the Declaration of Independence.
有人打算偷独立宣言
It's true.
是真的
I think I'd better put you gentlemen in touch with the FBI.
你们应该去跟调查局报告
- We've been to the FBI. - And?
去过了 结果呢 ?
They assured us that the Declaration cannot possibly be stolen.
他们说不可能被偷的
- They're right. - My friend and I are less certain.
他们说的很对 我们可没那么有信心
However, if we were given the privilege of examining the document...
要是我们能获准检视那份文件
we would be able to tell you for certain if it were actually in any danger.
就能肯定它是否有危险
What clo you think you're gonna find?
你认为你会找到什么 ?
We believe that there's an... encryption on the back.
我们相信那上面有一份… 密码在它背面
- An encryption, like a code? - Yes, ma'am. a
密码，就像代号 ? 是的
Of what?
什么的代号 ?
A... cartograph.
一个图
-Amap. - Yes, ma'am. a
地图? 是的
A map of what?
什么的地图 ?
The location of...
藏放一些…
..of hidden items of historic and intrinsic value.
颇具历史意义的… 稀世珍宝的地点
- A treasure map? - That's where we lost the FBI.
藏宝图? 调查局就不信这点
You're treasure-hunters, aren't you?
你们是寻宝猎人吗?
We're more like treasure-protectors.
我们更像是宝藏守护者
Mr. Brown, have personally seen the back of the Declaration of Independence,
我本人亲自看过独立宣言背面
and I promise you, the only thing there is a notation that reads. a
那苛面只有一段记载
"Original Declaration of Independence, dated...
"独立宣言正本，日期…"
"Four of July, 1776." Yes, ma'am.
"1776年7月4日"
But no map.
没有地图
It's invisible.
那是隐形的
Oh! Right.
是哦
And that's where we lost the Department of Homeland Security.
国安局也不信这点
What led you to assume there's this invisible map?
你们和赁什么认定有隐形地图?
We found an engraving on the stem of a 200-year-old pipe.
一具200年历史烟斗上的导刻
Owned by Freemasons.
由共济会员所拥有
- May I see the pipe? - We don't have it.
能让我看看烟斗吗 ? 烟斗不在我们手上
- Did Big Foot take it? - It was nice meeting you.
被大脚怪抢走了 ? 很高兴和能见到你
Nice to meet you, too.
我也是
And, you know, that really is a nice collection.
那收藏真的很不错
Must have taken you a long time to hunt down all that history.
你一定花了很多时间才找到它们
If it's any consolation, you had me convinced.
希望这能安奈你，你说服了我
It's not.
这没用
I was thinking, what if we go public, plaster the story all over the Internet?
何不公开这事 ? 在网络上公布一切
It's not like we have our reputations to worry about.
反正咱们的名声也够糟了
Although I don’t think that's exactly gonna scare lan away.
不过这样还是吓不跑伊四
180 years of searching, and I'm three feet away.
180年的搜寻，如今就在眼前
Of all the words written here about freedom. a
这僚于自由的论述中
there's a line here that's at the heart of all the others.
有一段话是最重要的
"But when a long train of abuses and usurpations,
"但当一连串的车政 与掠村"
pursuing invariably the same object,
"都是在追求同一目标"
evinces a design to reduce them under absolute despotism,
"意图以专制暴政压近人民"
it is their right, it is their duty to throw off such government
"人民就有权利 也有义务推翻这样的政府"
and provide new guards for their future security.”
"为未来的安全提出新的保障"
People don't talk that way anymore.
现在的人已经不这样说话了
- No idea what you said. - It means, if there's something wrong,
不过我不太明和白 如果出了事
those who have the ability to take action have the responsibility to take action.
有能力采取行动的人 就有责任该采取行动
I'm gonna steal it.
我要动手偷
What?
什么 ?
I'm gonna steal the Declaration of Independence.
我要偷独立宣言
Ben?
阿班 !
This is... huge.
这太冒险了
It's prison huge.
监狱级的冒险
You are gonna go to prison, you know that?
你会被抓去人的
Yeah, probably.
也许吧
So that would bother most people.
大部分的人是会怕的
lan's gonna try and steal it. And if he succeeds, he'll destroy the Declaration.
伊恩会下手偷它 他若成功，一定会毁了独立宣言
The fact is, the only way to protect the Declaration is to steal it.
保扩宣言的唯一办法就是偷走它
It's upside down.
恰好相反
I don't think there's a choice.
我别无选择
Ben, for God's sakes. a
班，和拜托你
it's like stealing a national monument. OK?
这就像是偷十迹
It's like stealing him.
就像偷他一样，不可能成功的
It can't be done. Not shouldn't be done. It can't be done.
不是该不该的问题，是不可能
Let me prove it to you.
我会证明给你看
OK, Ben, pay attention.
班，注意听了
I've brought you to the Library of Congress.
我为什么要带你到国会图书馆?
Why? Because it's the biggest library in the world.
因为这是世上最大的图书馆
Over 20 million books.
藏书超过二千万册
And they're all saying the same exact thing:
这些书全都说同一银话
listen to Riley.
"乖矢听莱利的"
What we have here, my friend, is an entire layout of the archives.
这是文物馆的平面详图
Short of builders’ blueprints.
只欠建筑病的蓝图
You've got construction orders, phone lines,
记载以施工顺序、电话线配线
water and sewage - it's all here.
水管和下水道配置图，全在这
Now. when the Declaration a is on display, OK,
独立宣言在展示时
itis surrounded by guards and video monitors
四周布满敬卫、录像监视器
and a little family from lowa and little kids on their eighth-grade field trip.
外地观光客、校外教学的小学生
And beneath an inch of bulletproof glass is an army of sensors and heat monitors
在一叶厚的防弹玻璃下 是一礁感应器和热传感器
that will go off if someone gets too close with a high fever.
若有人靠太近，警报就会激活
Now, when it's not on display,
至于在非展示时间
it is lowered into a four-foot-thick concrete, steel-plated vault...
它会被降下 放入一个墙厚四尺
that happens to be equipped with an electronic combination lock
用水泥与钢板建造的保管室 上面装有电子密码组合锁
and biometric access-cenial systems.
以及生物特征门控系统
You know. Thomas Edison tried and failed a nearly 2,000 times
爱迪生失败了近两千次
to develop the carbonized cotton-thread filament for the incandescent light bulb.
才用碳纤维做出灯泡
Edison?
爱迪生 ?
When asked about it. a he said. "I didn't fail. re
有人问他，他说，我没失败
I found out 2,000 ways how not to make a light bulb.”
我找到两千种不能做灯泡的方法
But he only needled to find one way to make it work.
他只需要找到一个成功的方法
The Preservation Room. Enjoy. Go ahead.
保存室，好好看看吧
Do you know what the Preservation Room is for?
你知道保存室是干嘛用的?
Delicious jams and jellies?
存放果营 ?
No. That's where they clean, repair and maintain
文物非展示期间
all the documents and the storage housings
清理修复、保养
when they're not on display or in the vault.
存放展示杠 都会送到这几
Now, when the case needs work they take it out of the vault, directly across the hall
展示框需要检验时 他们会把它从展示厅
and into the Preservation Room.
运到保存室
The best time for us. or lan, to steal it ee would be during the gala this weekend
咱们或伊恩动手的绝佳时机 就是在周末的庆祝晚会
when the guards are distracted by the VIPs upstairs.
到时警卫会分神留意宾客
But we'll make our way to the Preservation Room, where there's much less security.
咱们就设法摸进保存室 那儿的保全措施会较松散
Well. if lan... a
要是伊恩…
Preservation...
保存室
The gala, huh?
庆祝晚会
This might be possible.
这可能会成功
It might.
是很有可能
And we are in.
咱们进去了
There you are. Hello.
就是这根 你好
The hallway.
走廊
That's what I want.
我就需要这个
Game on.
开始了
I'll buy that.
够真了
Cool.
好耶
This just came for you.
有人送这给你
l hope it's not from Stan.
希望不是老板送的
"For the woman who has everything else... Thanks for listening. Paul Brown.”
送给只欠一件宝物的女人 谢谢你的倾听，保罗布朗
Abigail Chase.
雅碧却斯
Hey, Mike.
，麦克
- Let's do this by the book. - Hallway is secure.
照标准程序处理 走廊没问题
- Keep the document level. - No problem.
让文件保持水平 没问题
What have you got?
怎么回事 ?
The heat sensor went off in the Declaration frame.
文件框的热感应器丈报激活
Run full diagnostics, then I want them all changed out.
进行全面检查，然后全部换掉
Our evil plan is working.
那亚计画奏效了
Ben, are you sure that we should...?
你确定要这人么做?
Riley.
莱利
- Can you hear me? - Unfortunately, yeah.
听得见我吗 ? 真不幸，我听得见
We're all set in here.
一切就绪
You want to go around to the front and present your invitation.
请绕到正门
Howely.
你好
I need your invitation and your ID, please.
请出示邀请卡和身分证明
How do you look?
情况如何?
- Not bad. - Mazel tov.
还不坏 恭喜了
This is it.
时候到了
For you.
给你
- Oh, Mr. Brown. a - Dr. Chase.
布朗先生 却斯博士
- What are you doing here? - Is that that hot girl?
你怎么会在这儿? 这是那个辣妹吗 ?
- How cloes she look? - [made a last-minute donation. A big one.
她穿的辣吗 ? 我赶在最后捐了一大笔
Well, on that subject, thank you for your wonderful gift.
说到这个，谢谢你的礼物
- Oh, you did get it? Good. - Yes, thank you.
你路到了?很好 是的，谢谢你
You know, I really couldn't accept something like that normally, but...
通常我不能接受礼物
I really want it.
不过我真的很想要它
- Well, you needled it. - Come on, Romeo, get outta there.
你需要它 快离开那几，大情圣
l have been wondering, though, what the engraving indicated
我一直在想，那雕刻暗示什么
on the pipe that Big Foot took.
就是大脚怪拿走的那个
Hi.
旷
- Here you go. - Oh, Dr. Herbert. this is Mr. Brown. a
来了 赫伯博士，这位是布朗先生
- Hi. - Hi there.
旷 你好
- Who's the stiff? - Here, why don't you let me take that?
这果子是谁 ? 我帮你拿这杯
- So you can take that off his hands. - Thank you.
这样你好拿他手上那杯 谢诈
A toast, yeah?
干杯
To high treason.
数叛国者
That's what these men were committing when they signed the Declaration.
就是那些签署独立宣言的人
Had we lost the war, they would have been hanged, beheaded, drawn and quartered,
要是打输了，他们就会被处死 五马分己
and - Oh! Oh, my personal favorite - and had their entrails cut out and burned!
还有我最喜欢的 控出内脏用火焚烧
So. here's to the men a who did what was considered wrong
数那些做别人认为是错事
in order to do what they knew was right.
却是做他们自认是正确事情的人
What they knew was right.
他们很清楚那么做是对的
Well, good night.
那么，晚安
- Good night.
晚安
Yeah!
好耶
OK, go! Go!
上 !
This better work.
最好有效
Clear!
安全 !
- On. - Door one. 30 seconds.
点燃了 第一道门，30秒
How does it look?
怎样 ?
It's working. It's working...
起作用了
Unbelievable.
不可思议
Second door. 90 seconds.
第二道门，90秒
Well done, boys. Let's go.
干的好
- We're in the elevator. - OK.
进电梯了 好
I'm gonna turn off the surveillance cameras. Ready?
我要侨闭监视器了
three... Now.
三…就是现在
Ben Gates. a
班盖兹
you are now the Invisible Man.
你现在是隐形人了
- I'm here. - Give me the letters for her password.
我进来了 把字母报出来
What clo you got for me?
是哪些 ?
Hit me with it.
告诉我吧
A-E-F-G...
A-E-F-G…:
L-O-R-V-Y.
工-O-R-V一Y
Anagrams being listed.
字谜组合结果
OK.
好
Top results: "A glove fry.”
最佳解是… A Glove Fry
"A very golf.”
A Very Gol了T
"Fargo levy.”
Fargo Levy
"Gravy floe. Valey frog.”
GOravy Floe，Valey Frog
Also "Ago fly rev.”
还有Ago FLyY Rev
"Grove fly a.”
Grove FE1y A
"Are fly gov.”
Are F1y7 Gov
"Era fly gov.”
Era Fly Gov
- "Elf gov ray.” - It's "Valley Forge.”
E1E gov fray 是Valley Forge
"Valley For...” I don't have that on my computer.
Valley Forge 计算机上没这个组合
It's "Valley Forge” - she pressed the E and L twice.
她输入E和[两次
Valley Forge was a turning point in the American Revolution.
Valley Forge 代表着 美国革命史上的转折点
Can I marry your brain?
你未免太聪明了
We're in.
我进来了
Hello.
你好
Ben, you're doing great.
做的很好
Ben, pick it up.
动作快点
You got about one...
你还有大约…
We own video.
我们控制监视器了
- [lost my feed. - What?
我失去影像了 什么 ?
I don't know where anyone is. l have nothing.
不知道别人在于嘛 我什么都看不到
Ben, I have no... a Ben, I have nothing.
什么都没有 班，我什么都看不到
Get out of there. Get out of there now.
快离开，马上出去
I'm taking the whole thing. I'll get it out in the elevator.
我会带着文件去搭电梯
What are you talking about? Is it heavy?
那很重吗 ?
Shaw. Door three, one minute. a
老萧 第三道门，1分钟
Gates.
盖 兹
What was that?
那是什么 ?
Who's shooting?
是谁开的枪?
- Damn. - He's got the bloody map!
可恶 他妈的地图被他拿走了
Are you still there? Ben?
你还在吗?
I'm in the elevator.
我在电梯里
- lan's here. There was, uh, shooting. - [hate that guy.
伊恩也来了，他开了枪 我真恨那家伙
Hey, Rebecca. Do you have a Paul Brown on that list?
蔓贝亮 名单上有保罗布朗这个人吗?
Paul Brown?
保罗布朗 ?
No. Not here.
没有
Have a good night.
晚安了
Are you trying to steal that?
你想偷东西 ?
It's $35.
这要35元
- For this? - Yeah.
买这个? 对
- That's a lot. - Hey, I don't make the prices.
还真贵 价钱又不是我订的
Il have $32...
我这儿有32元
57.
…57分 ?
We take Visa.
我们收信用卡
This is Mike. Sublevel three. l have an alert.
我是麦克，有状况
Where are you, Ben?
你在哪儿，班?
- Where are you? - Stop talking.
你在哪儿 ? 闭嘴
Start the van.
发动车子
Ben, the... a the mean Declaration lady's behind you.
文物馆的弛婆娘在你后面
Hey.
旷
Oh, it's you. Hello.
是你啊 你好
Mr. Brown, what's going on? What's that?
这是怎么回事?那是什么 ?
- It's a souvenir. - Really?
纪念品 是吗 ?
Stop chatting and get in the van.
别聊天了，快上车
Code red. Code red. We have a break-in.
红色警报，有人阁入
Lock it down. Nobody leaves the building. Get the FBI on the phone.
全面封锁，不准任何人离开 快通知调查局
- Did you enjoy the party? - Yeah.
庆祝会好玩吗 ? 还好
- Oh, my God. - Oh, my God! You did not...?
天哪 老天，你不会吧
- No... - Security! Over here!
不 警卫! 这几!
- Give me that! - It's yours. Take it.
把那给我 ! 你拿去吧
Security!
警卫 !
- Over here! Security! - Got you.
在这几! 好了
Go.
快走!
Viktor! Move!
维多 ! 快开车 !
- We can't just let her go! - We can. Go!
不能放她走 可以的1快走!
- Security, over here! - Wait. No, hold it. a
警卫! 这几! 等等!等等!
Hold it!
等等!
- Wha...? - Oh. bad. a
怎么…? 糟了
- What do you want? - Give me the document.
你要干骂 ? 把东西给我
Bad. bad. bad! a
糟了
- Let me go! - Just bring her!
放开我 快带走她
No! No!
不!不!
- That's... - Go! Go!
真是… 快追 !
And just who might you be?
你是谁啊 ?
- Once we catch them what do we do? - I'm working on it.
咱们追上去要干嘛 ? 我正在想
Right turn, right turn.
右转
Why don't you just pass me that document? Then we can all go home.
把文件给我，对大伙都好
Oh, no. a
糟了
Skidding, skidding, skidding.
打浊
- Oh, no! a - Holy Lord!
我的妈呀
- Help! - No! If she falls, the document falls. a
她掉下去，文件就没了
Get me next to her.
把我送到她劣边
- Thank you. - No!
谢诈 不!
Got it. Go on.
拿到了，动手吧
Abigail!
雅碧 !
Come on. Jump.
快跳!
- We lost them. - That's all right. This... is what we need.
他们和逃了 无所谓，我们只要这个
Well done. Gates. Well done. a
有你的，盖兹，真有你的
- Are you all right? - No! Those lunatics...
你没事吧 ? 不好，那些疯子…
- You're not hurt, are you? - You are all lunatics!
没受伤吧 ? 你们都是疯子
- Are you hungry? - What?
你铁吗 ? 什么 ?
Are you all right?
你没事吧 ?
Still a little on edge from being shot at, but I'll be OK. Thanks for asking.
我吓坏了，不过还好，多谢锋心
Yeah, well, I'm not all right. Those men have the Declaration of Independence!
那些人拿走了独立宣言
- She lost it? - They don't have it.
她型丢了? 他们没拿到手
See? OK? Now could you please stop shouting?
看到了吧 ? 现在能不能麻烦你闭哎 ?
- Give me that! - You're still shouting. It's starting to annoy.
还给我 ! 你还在乱吼，真烦
You'd do well, Dr. Chase. re to be a bit more civilized in this instance.
你可以表现更有教养一点
If this is the real one, what did they get?
这若是真品，他们手上那份呢?
A souvenir.
是纪念品
I thought it'd be a good idea to have a duplicate. It turned out I was right.
我想复制品可能会有用 果然没料错
l actually had to pay for the souvenir and the real one, so you owe me $35, plus tax.
事实上，我还付钱买下它们 所以你欠我35元，外加税金
- Genius. - Who were those men?
真天才 那些人是谁?
Just the guys we warned you were gonna steal the Declaration.
我们说过要偷独立宣言的人
And you didn't believe us.
而你并不相信我们
We did the only thing we could do to keep it safe.
我们只好设法保扩它的安全
Verdammt! Give me that!
东西给我 !
You know something? You're shouting again.
你又再乱吼了
I'm pretty sure she was swearing, too.
她还乱久人呢
Well, we probably deserve that.
或许我们也该贸
Ladies and gentlemen...
各位来窒
Ladies and gentlemen, my name is Peter Sadusky. I'm the agent in charge.
我是彼德沙斯基，现场由我负责
Il wanna reassure you, you are not in danger in any way.
我至保证，各位没有任何危险
If we all cooperate, we'll get through this with as little frustration as possible.
只要大估合作 我们很快就能排除这个小状况
Thank you.
谢诈
Get positive IDs. Search everyone, including the security staff.
查看证件、搜查每个人 包括警卫人员
If they refuse, detain them and get warrants.
有人拒绝就加以拘留并申请拘标
Yes, Agent Hendricks? You have something?
有事吗 ? 韩得利探员?
- This isn't a day for "Um..." - We got a tip several days ago
现在不是说"嗯"的时候 我们曾获报
that someone was going to steal the Declaration of Independence.
说有人要偷独立宣言
Do we have a name on the tipster?
报案的是谁?
There was no file opened. We didn't find the information credible.
没设档案 我们不认为这消息可靠
How about now?
现在可以设了吧?
There is not a treasure map on the back of the Declaration of Independence.
独立宣言的背面没有什么地图
And there's no chance anyone can steal this either.
也没有人和能偷走它
I leveled with you 100 percent. Everything I told you was the truth.
我对你100%的诚实以告
I want that document. Mr. Brown. a
我要那份文件，布朗先生
OK, my name's not Brown. It's Gates.
好吧，我不姓布衣，我姓盖兹
I leveled with you 98 percent.
我只吐露了98%的实情
Wait a minute, clic you just say "Gates"?
你说你姓盖兹 ?
Gates?
盖兹?
You're that family with the conspiracy theory about the Founding Fathers?
就是你们家族 主张建国英雄们有阴谋
- It's not a conspiracy theory. - Per se.
那不是什么阴谋 本质上来说不是
You know what? I take it back. You're not liars. You're insane.
我收回 你不是骗子，你是疯子
There's a copy of the Declaration on display now?
改陈列独立宣言的复本了?
- Yes. we decided to... a - Leave it there.
是的 很好，这样就能鱼目混珠了
The guests know something happened, but they don't know what.
来宾知道出事了 但不知道是什么事
They got him with a Taser at the service entrance. He doesn't remember a thing.
密贼用电击棒，他什么都不记得
Also, we found bullet casings.
我们找到弹帝
Dic we get a description from the other guards?
其它警卫有证词吗 ?
- Which guards? - The guards that were fired upon.
哪个警卫 ? 开枪的那个
There weren't any other guards on patrol down here.
下面没有其它鳌卫
So...
那…
who was shooting, who were they shooting at,
是谁开的枪? 这又是对谁开枪 ?
and why weren't they getting along?
他们为什么会对上彼此?
You can't seriously intend to run chemical tests
你不能在一辆疾驶的车上
on the Declaration of Independence in the back of a moving van.
对独立宣言进行化学实验
We have a clean-room environment all set up.
我们准备了一间无尘室
EDS suits, a particulate air filtration system, the whole shebang.
防扩衣、空气滤清器…一应俱全
- Really? - We can't go back there.
是吗 ? 不能去那儿
What? Why not?
为什么?
This is the guy. Dr. Herbert said Dr. Chase introduced him as Mr. Brown.
就是他，却斯博士说他叫布朗
Not on the guestlist.
宾客名单上没有
Now, the gift-store clerk - she said he seemed... Well. she said "flustered." a
礼品店店员说他的样子很慌张
He tried to walk out with a copy of the Declaration of Independence
还想拿走独立宣言的复制品
without paying.
顺手牵羊
He paid with a Visa.
他用信用卡付的焉
"Charge to Benjamin Gates.”
持卡人是班杰明盖北
A credit-card slip?
信用卡收据?
Dude, we're on the grid.
老大，我们完了
They'll have your records from forever. They'll have my records from forever.
他们会查出你所有的记录
I know. I Know. It's only a matter of minutes before the FBI shows up at my front door.
我知道，调查局随时都会找上我
What clo we do?
那要怎么办?
- We need those letters. - What letters?
我们需要那些信 什么售?
You know, get off the road, take a right.
下高速公路，右转
You have the original Silence Dogood letters? Did you steal those, too?
你有沈默杜十德的信正本 ? 那些也是你偷来的 ?
We have scans of the originals.
我们扫虹了正本
- Quiet, please. - How'd you get scans?
拜托你闭跑 你怎么扫瞄的?
Oh, I know the person who has the originals. Now shush.
我认识拥有正本的人，安静
- Why do you need them? - She really can't shut her mouth, can she?
你为什么要用那些信 ? 她就是不能闭踢
I'll tell you what, look. I will let you hold onto this
听着，我让你拿着这个
if you'll promise to shut up, please.
只要你答应财嘴，和拜托
Thank you.
谢诈
- Ben, you know what you have to do. - [know what to do.
你知道你该怎么做 我知道
I'm just trying to think of anything else we could do.
我是想先看看有没有别的办法
Well, not to be a... nudge,
我不想讨人大
but you do realize how many people we have after us.
不过你知道有多少人在追我们 ?
We probably have our own satellite by now.
搞不好有专属卫星在追踪我们了
It took you all of two seconds to decide to steal the Declaration of Independence.
你才花两秒就决定动手偷文件
Yeah, but I didn't think l was gonna personally have to tell my dad about it.
对，但我没想过得跟我爸告白
Hey, not cool! Not cool!
这可不聪明 !
Let me go!
放我走!
OK. You're let go. Go, shoo.
好，你可以走了，快走
I'm not going. Not without the Declaration.
没有独立宣言我哪都不去
You're not going with the Declaration.
你不能带走它
Yes, Lam. I'm not letting it out of my sight, so I'm going.
我不会让它离开我，我也要去
Wait. You're not going with us with the Declaration.
你不能跟我们带着它一起走
- Yes. lam. a - No, you're not.
我要去 你不行去
Look, if you wanted to leave me behind,
你要是想丢下我
you shouldn't have told me where you were going.
就不该告诉我你们要去哪
Clear.
没人
What the...
不会吧
Now we're getting somewhere.
这下有收获了
They're digital scans of letters to the editor of The New England Courant.
他们扫了瞄了新英格兰报
Written 1722.
1772年的所收到的读者来信
They're all from the same person. "Your humble servant, Silence Dogood.”
发信者是同一个人 "你谦卑的仆人 沈黑杜十德"
Gentlemen...
各位
why is this word capitalized?
沉歌这个字为什么大窟 ?
Because it's important?
因为它很重要 ?
Because it's a name.
因为这是个名字
OK, I got it. When Ben Franklin was only 15 years old
富兰克林15岁时
he secretly wrote 14 letters to his brother's newspaper
秘密写了14封信给他哥的报社
pretending to be a middle-aged widow named Silence Dogood.
伪装成名为沈软杜十德的寡妇
These letters were written by Benjamin Franklin.
信其实都是富兰克林写的
Looks OK.
看起来没问题
- Park a couple of blocks away. - Well, how long do you think we got?
停在几个路口外 我们有多久时间 ?
I'm gonna give them a couple of hours at least. hope.
至少几个小时吧，我希望
What clo we do about her? I've got some duct tape in the back.
那她呢 ? 我后车厢还有些胶带
No, that won't be necessary. She won't be any trouble.
不用了，她不会碍事的
- Promise you won't be any trouble. - [ promise.
答应我你不会碍事
See? She's curious.
看吧 ?她也很好奇
Here's what I got on Gates. A degree in American History from Georgetown,
盖兹拥有… 乔治城大学美国史学位
a degree in Mechanical Engineering at MIT. a
还有麻省理工的电机学位
Navy ROTC and Naval Diving and Salvage Training Center.
海军预备军官团、潜水救难中心
What in the world did this guy want to be when he grew up?
他到底想干什么 ?
We keep our focus on Gates.
继续找盖兹
Run him to ground.
还到他为止
Compile a family-and-friends list. Closest relative first.
收集家族朋友名单，先找近亲
I want to find out who this guy is.
我想查清楚这家伙是谁
Dad.
区
Where's the party?
在哪开的派对?
Well... I'm in a little trouble.
这个嘛… 我车了一点麻烦
- ls she pregnant? - Well. if she is. a
她怀孕了? 是的话
are you gonna leave the woman carrying your grandchild standing out in the cold?
是的话，你会让怀你孙子的女人 站在外面吹冷风吗?
I look pregnant?
我像怀了有吗?
This better not be about that dumb treasure.
这最好跟那个蠢宝藏无从
Well. have a seat. a Make yourselves comfortable.
坐吧，不用拘束
There's some pizza. It's still warm. I think. a
这儿有些披萨，还是温的
Dadi...
区
I need the Silence Dogood letters. Yeah. it's about the treasure. a
我需要沉默杜十德的信 这的确跟宝藏有人儿
And he dragged you two into this nonsense?
是他拖你们下水的?
- Literally. - volunteered.
没错 我是自愿的
Well. unvolunteer. a before you waste your life.
快退出，免得浪费你的人生
- Knock it off. Dad. a - Sure, sure, Know, I'm the family kook.
别说了，和区 没错，我是家里的怪胎
l have a job, a house, health insurance.
我有工作、马子、健保
At least l had your mother, for however brief a time. At least l had you.
至少我还有你妈，虽然时间短暂 至少我还有你
What cdo you have? Him?
你有什么?他吗?
Look, if you just give us the letters, we're gone.
把信给我们，我们就走
You disappoint me, Ben.
你真令我失望，儿了
Well, maybe that's the real Gates-family legacy. Sons who disappoint their fathers.
也许这才是盖兹家的传统 儿子老是令老符失望
Get out. Take your troubles with you.
出去，涡着你的麻烦离开
Il found the Charlotte.
我找到夏绿还号了
The Charlotte?
夏绿蒂号 ?
- You mean she was a ship? - Yeah. she was beautiful. a
是一舰船? 很美
It was amazing, Dad.
真的很棒
And the treasure?
那宝藏宪?
No, no. But we found another clue a that led us here.
没有，我们找到另一个线索
Yeah, and that'll lead you to another clue.
是啊，那会引你找到另一个线索
And that's all you'll ever find, is another clue. Don't you get it, Ben?
你只会一直找到线索 你还不懂 ?
I finally figured it out.
我早想清楚了
The legend says that the treasure was buried to keep it from the British.
传说宝藏被埋藏 以避免被英军发现
But what really happened was the legend was invented,
事实是，传说是杜撰的
to keep the British occupied searching for buried treasure.
那是为了让英军忙于搜寻宝藏
The treasure is a myth.
宝藏只是个故事
l refuse to believe that.
我拒绝相信
Well, you can believe what you want. You're a grown person. What am I doing?
随你爱信什么，你已经长大了
Do what you want, Ben. Do what you want.
随你想做什么，随便你
He's probably right. You don't even know if there is another clue.
他可能是对的 你不知道还有没有线索
Well, l can think of a way where we could find out. And we can find out right now.
我能想办法查清楚 现在就能查清楚
Looks like animal skin.
看来像是动物的皮
- How old is it? - At least 200 years.
年代有多和久 ? 至少两百年
- Really? You sure? - Pretty darn.
真的?你确定 ? 不会错的
Now if this thing's in invisible ink, how clo we look at it?
如果是用隐形墨水，要怎么看?
Throw it in the oven.
把它去进烧箱
- No. - Uh-uh.
不行
Ferrous sulfate inks can only be brought out with heat.
硫化亚铁时水要靠热气才能显现
- Yes. but this... a - It's very old.
对，但这个… 很十老
This is very old, and we can't tisk compromising the map.
非常十老 不能冒险损伤地图
You need a reagent.
你要用试剂
Dad. it’s really late. Why don't you get some rest?
区，很晚了，去睡吧
I'm fine.
我不和急
Lemons.
用柠檬
- You can't do that. - But it has to be done.
不能这么做 我非做不可
Then someone who is trained to handle antique documents is gonna do it.
那就让受过专业训练的人来做吧
OK.
好吧
Now, if there is a secret message,
要是这上面有秘密讯息
itll probably be marked by a symbol in the upper right-hand corner.
就可能会有一个记号 罕在机上方的角落里
That's right.
没错
lam so getting fired for this.
我这么做背定会被炒锭鱼
I told you. You need heat.
我说过了 要用热气
See?
看吧?
- We need more juice. - We need more heat.
要更多的果汗 还要有更多热气
That's not a map.
那不是地图吧
- Is it? - More clues. What a surprise.
那是吗 ? 又是线索，真是个惊喜
Are those latitudes and longitudes?
纬度和经度 ?
That's why we need the Silence Dogood letters.
所以我们才需要那些信
- That's the key? - Yeah. "The key in Silence undetected.”
那就是钥是 "人钥是沉默隐其中"
Dad. can we have the letters now? a
答，和能不能把信给我们 ?
Will somebody please explain to me what these magic numbers are?
拜托解释一下这些密码代表什么
- It's an Ottendorf cipher. - That's right.
这是奥腾多夫密码 没错
Oh. OK. a
好吧
- What's an Ottendorf cipher? - They're just codes.
那是什么 ? 就是代码
Each of these three numbers corresponds to a word in a key.
每三个号码对应解答里的一个字
Usually a random book or a newspaper article.
通常是一本书或一篇报上的文章
In this case, a the Silence Dogood letters.
而这儿指的是沈软杜十德的信
So it's like the page number of the key text,
这是指解答文的页码
the line on the page, and the letter in that line.
行数和该行的第几个字母
So. Dad. where are the letters? ee
和爸，那些信呢 ?
You know, it's just by sheer happenstance that his grandfather...
他和从区能发现那些信
- Dad. - ..even found them.
区 根本就是一个意外
They were in an antique desk from the press room...
信就放在新英格兰报
- Dad. - ..0f The New England Courant.
区 印刷室里
- That's a newspaper. - Dad. where are the letters? a
就是报社里 那些信呢 ?
I don't have them. son.
不在我手上，儿子
- What? - [don't have them.
什么 ? 不在我手上
Where are they?
那是在哪儿 ?
I donated them to the Franklin Institute in Philadelphia.
捐给费城的富兰克林纪念馆了
Time to go.
该走了
I still can't believe it. All this time no one knew what was on the back.
我真不敢相信，这么久以来 竟然没人知道这苛面有东西
The back of what?
什么的背面 ?
No!
不!
- Oh, my God. Oh, my God. - know.
天哪、我的老天 我知道
Oh, my God. What have you done? This is... this is the...
这是…你做了什么? 这是….
- l know! - This is the Declaration of Independence.
我知道 独立宣言
Yes. And it's very delicate.
对，而且它还很脆弱
You stole it?
你偷来的?
Dad, I can explain, but I don't have time. It was necessary. And you saw the cipher.
我能解释，不过我没时间 我别无选择，你也看到密码了
And that will lead to another clue, a and that will lead to another clue!
那只会引领你找到更多线索
There is no treasure. l wasted 20 years of my life.
根本没有什么宝藏 我浪费了二二年的光阴
And now you've destroyed yours.
现在你也毁了你的人生
And you pulled me into all this.
还害我也消了这趟浑水
Well. we can't have that. a
我们不会害你的
Come in!
快进来 !
I'm in here.
我在这儿 1!
FBI, right?
调查局，对吧 ?
You gonna untie me?
你们会帮我松绑吧 ?
And you have no idea where he's going?
你不知道他去哪了?
- Well, wouldn't I have told you if I did? - Would you?
我要是知道早跟你说了 你会说吗 ?
He tied me to a chair.
他把我绑在椅子上
The garage is empty, but there’s a Cadillac DeVille registered to Patrick Gates.
车库是空的 但派属克盖益名下有辆凯迪拉克
And he stole my car.
他还丛了我的车
Don't worry, Mr. Gates, we'll find your car. And your son.
别担心，我们会找到你的车 还有你儿子
Your dad's got a sweet ride.
你葡的车还真不错
I think we should change clothes.
我们该换个衣服
We look kind of conspicuous, don't you think?
这样太醒目了，你说呢?
I'd love to go shopping, too, but we have no money.
我很想镍街购物，但我们没钱
Here. I took this from his house. a
我从他家拿了这个
He usually tucks a few hundred dollars somewhere between those pages.
他通常会在里边夹个几百元
- Common Sense. How appropriate. - When are we gonna get there?
"常识"，还真合适 什么时候会到?我饿了
I'm hungry. This car smells weird.
这车子有股怪味
Excuse me.
抱娄、借过
Excuse me. Oops, sorry, sir. Excuse me.
对不起，借过
That's OK.
没估系
$-S-A-N-D.
S-S-A-N-D
OK.
好
You're sure this is right?
你确定没错?
S-S-A...
S-S-A...
No, N. a
不对，是T
- That is an N. - It doesn't look like an N.
这是N没错啊 看起来不像
You know what? Here. Last one. OK?
这是最后一个了
- One more dollar. - Thank you.
再一元 谢诈
Go get the last four letters.
把最后四个字母抄来
Go get 'em, chief. Come on.
快去抄吧
OK. "The vision to see the treasured past
"看见珍藏的过去"
comes as the timely shadow crosses in front of the house of pass and...”
"要适时的追随阴影" "越过派斯和
"Pass and...” what?
派斯和什么 ?
"Pass and...”
派斯和…-
What's going on?
怎么回事 ?
- I'm not sure. - What's up?
我不确定 怎么了?
So you show up at your father’s door and say you're in trouble
你跑到你区面前，说你有麻烦
and the first thing he assumes is I'm pregnant.
他最先想到的却是我怀孕了
Is there a question in there?
这有问题吗?
I think there's an interesting story in there.
我想这一定有个有趣的故事
Well, my father thinks I've been a little too cavalier in my personal life.
我爸认为我的私生活太随便了
-lsee. - Let me ask you something.
这样啊 我问你
Have you ever told someone - not a relative - "I love you?"
你有没有跟别人说过 而且不是对你亲戚，说"我爱你"?
Yes.
有
More than one someone?
而且这人还不只一个?
Oh. Well, then my father would say
那我爸也会说
you've been a little too cavalier in your personal life, too.
你很随便
So you get your sense of absolute certainty from him, do you?
所以你的顽国也是得自他的真传
Well. I'm sure I don't know a what you mean.
我不明白你的意思
Well, you're certain the treasure is real, despite what anyone else thinks.
不管别人怎么想 你都确定宝藏是真的
No, but I hope it's real.
不，但我希望那是真的
I mean, I've dreamt it’s real a since my grandfather told me about it.
公苍说过之后，我一直想着宝藏
But I want to hold it. I feel like I'm so close. I can taste it. a
我感党它就近在眼前
But I just... l just want to know it's not just something in my head or in my heart.
我只想知道这不是我的幻想
People don't really talk that way, you know.
人们现在已经不这样说话了
I know. But they think that way.
我知道，但人们会这样想
Hey.
旷
- Did you get it? Riley? - Oh, I got it.
都抄到了? 都抄到了
"The vision to see the treasured past comes
"看见珍藏的过去"
as the timely shadow crosses in front of the house of Pass and Stow.”
"要适时的追随阴影" "越过派斯和史托"
Now, "Pass and Stow.” of course, re referring to...
"派斯和史托"指的当然是…
- The Liberty Bell. - Why do you have to do that?
自巾钟 你们千骂老是这么聪明啊?
Well. John Pass and John Stow a cast the bell.
怕斯和史托铸造了那口钟
OK. Well. then, what does ee the rest of this mean?
其它的部份呢?
Wait... "The vision to see the treasured past" must refer to a way to read the map.
"看见珍藏的过去" 一定是指看到地图的方法
Well, [ thought the cipher was the map.
我以为密码就是地图
No, the cipher was a way to find the way to read the map.
密码是找到看地图的方法
And the way to read the map can be found
要看地图得"适时追随"
where the "timely shadow” crosses in front of the Liberty Bell.
越过自由钟的阴影
Crosses in front of the "house" of the Liberty Bell. Independence Hall.
越过放自由钟的独立厅的阴影
Right, so "timely shadow" - it's a specific time.
所以适时的阴影是指某个时间
- Right. - What time?
对 什么时间 ?
What time? What time?
什么时间?了什么时间 ?
Wait a minute. wait. a You're gonna love this.
等等，你们会爱死这个的
Excuse me, can I see one of those a hundred-dollar bills I paid you with?
能不能让我看我刚付的百元钞 ?
No.
不能
Oh. Well. here. ee l have this diver’s watch.
我这儿有只潜水表
It's called a Submariner. I dive with it. It's actually quite valuable.
是劳力士，很昂贵的
- You can use it as collateral. - Whatever.
就合它当担保品吧 随便啦
Thank you.
谢了
On the back of a hundred-dollar bill is an etching of Independence Hall
百元钞的背后印有独立厅
- based on a painting done in... - Hello.
这幅画是… 哈鹃
Thank you. ..in the 1780s. who... a
谢谢，那是1780年的版画
The artist was actually a friend of Benjamin Franklin's. It's wonderful.
该画作家是富兰克林的朋友
- Fascinating. - Hold this.
你好懂啊 拿着
OK.
好
I'm not going anywhere.
我不会乱跑的
Now, I think that if we look a at this clock tower...
只要仔细看钟塔
..we may find the specific time.
可能就能找出正确的时间
- What clo you see? - 2:22,
你看到什么 ? 2点22分
- What time is it now? - Almost three.
现在几点? 快3点了
- We missed it. - No. we didn't. a
时间已经过了 没有
We didn't miss it because...
还没错过，因为…
You don't know this? I-l know something about history that you don't know.
你们不知道 ? 我竟然知道你们不知道的事
I'd be very excited to learn about it, Riley.
我很乐意向你请教
Well, hold on one second, let me just... let me just take in this moment.
等等，让我享受一下此刻
This is... this is cool.
真酷
Is this how you feel all the time? Because, you know... Except for now, of course.
原来你们就是这种感觉 ? 当然此刻除外
- Riley! - All right.
莱利 ! 好啦 !
What I know is that daylight savings wasn't established until World War I.
我知道日光节约时间，…: 是在一炊世界大战之后才开始的
If i's 3pm now, OK, that means in 1776, it would be 2pm.
如果现在是下午3点 那在1776年就是下午2点
- Let's go. - Riley, you're a genius.
快去吧 莱利，你是天才
Yeah.
好耶
Do you actually know who the first person to suggest daylight savings was?
你们知道是谁提议用节约时间 ?
- Benjamin Franklin.
富兰克林 就是富兰克林
Is this real?
这是真钞吗 ?
Just tell me what you told my friend.
告诉我你跟我朋友说了什么
Just a bunch of letters. I can't remember.
只是一堆字母，我记不得了
Can you remember which ones you were gonna tell him next?
记得接下来要告诉他什么吗 ?
Yeah. here. S-T-O-W. a
记得，在这 "S-T-0O-旭”
Top results: Liberty Bell and Independence Hall.
(搜寻结果 : 自由钟与独立厅)
Imagine its impact back in the 18th century.
想象它在18世纪引发的冲击
It could have been seen for miles around. a which was exactly its purpose,
数英里之外就能看到它 这也是它建造的目的
because it served as a beacon. as it were. re for people to collect and hear...
它就像灯塔，让人们…
Good stuff.
好东西
It gained a place in history on July 8, 1776,
1776年，华盛顿生日那天 在最后一炎裂缝扩大后
when the Liberty Bell tolled for the first public reading
自由钟就永远的退休了
Eventually, it was moved from its place
最后它从独立厅移到了…
- Idiot. - Who?
白痪 谁?
- Me. - What?
我 怎么?
It's not here. It's there.
不是这儿，是那儿
Come on.
走吧
- What bell is this? - It's the Centennial Bell.
这是什么钟 ? 圣塔尼钟
It replaced the Liberty Bell in 1876.
1876年取代了自由钟
There it is.
在那儿
All right. I'm gonna go clown there, and you meet me in the signing room.
我去，到签署室等我
- OK? All right. - OK.
可以吗? 可以
All right, let's go.
好，我们走
3:22. My idea.
3点22分，是我想到的
Hey. What'd you score?
找到什么了 ?
I found this.
找到这个
Some kind of ocular device.
特殊眼镜
"The vision to see the treasured past.” Let me take this.
"看见珍藏的过去"? 这个给我
Aw, they're like early American X-ray specs.
这就像古早的X光眼镜
Benjamin Franklin invented something like these.
富兰克林发明过类似的东西
I think he invented these.
我想他就是发明了这个
So. what do we do with them? a
要拿它干瘦 ?
We look through it.
戴上它来看
Here, help me.
帮有我
- Careful. - You think?
小心点 怎样 ?
- What? - It's just that the last time this was here
怎么样 ? 这文件上一灾出现在这几
it was being signed.
正是它被签署的时候
- Ben, there's another tour coming. - Turn it over.
马上又有观光导览要来了 翻过去
- Careful. - Spectacles.
小心 眼镜
What clo you see?
你看到什么了 ?
What is it? Is it a treasure map?
是什么?藏宝图?
It says, "Heere at the wall.” spelled with two E's.
上面写"就在墙…这儿(Heere)" 拼字还用了两个e
Take a look.
你看看
Wow.
哇
Why can't they just say, "Go to this place, and here's the treasure, spend it wisely?”
干骂不写 "宝藏在此，小心花用"
- Oh, no.
糟了
How'd they find us?
他们怎么找到我们的 ?
Well, lan has nearly unlimited resources. And he's smart.
伊恩有很多资源，他也够聪明
I don't think we can get out of here without being spotted.
我们不可能不被看到而离开
Well. we don't want them to have a the Declaration, or the glasses.
不能让他们拿到独立宣言或眼镜
But we especially don't want them to have them both together.
特别是两者一起
- So what do we do? - We separate the lock from the key.
那要怎么办? 把锁跟钥是分开
- We're splitting up. - Good idea.
分开走 好主意
Really?
你确定 ?
I'll take this.
我带着这个
And those. You keep that. Meet me at the car and call me if you have any problems.
还有那个，你们拿着那个 到车上会含，有状况打电话给我
Like if we get caught and killed?
像是被捉或被人宣掉吗 ?
Yeah. That would be a big problem. Take care of her.
对，那样麻烦可就大了 照顾好她
- L will.
我会的
We're on him.
跟上他了
There he is.
他在那儿
- Let's walk this way. - Wait up.
往这边 等等
- Shaw. look. There's the others. a - [got it.
你看…是另外两个人 我来
Viktor, meet me at Fifth and Chestnut. Fifth a and Chestnut. They're heading your way.
维多，到第五街和枝子街碰头 他们往你那边去了
- Look out! Look out! - Riley!
证开 ! 莱利 !
- There they are! Move! - Move!
在那几，快 快走
- Time to run. - Keep up. Viktor! Move. Come on.
快跑! 维多，跟紧点，快
In here.
进这儿
- Come on. - Follow me.
跟我来
That way.
那碗
If you're not a steak, you don't belong here.
你如果不是牛排，就不能待在这
I'm just trying to hice from my ex-husband.
我在躲我前夫
- Who, baldy? - Yes.
哪个? 光头? 对
Honey, stay as long as you like.
你想待多久随你
Oh, thank you. Thank you.
谢诈
You want something?
你要买什么 ?
- Do you want something? - Shut up.
你想买什么吗 ? 闭踢啦
I see why you left him.
我明白你为什么要离开他了
Go around. Go around.
绕过去 !
Gates!
盖冀1
Aw. come on! a
拜托 !
- Where were you? - Hiding.
你跑去哪了? 租坏人啊
Come on. Let's go, let's go.
来吧，我们走
lan. lan, I've got em. They're heading toward City Hall.
伊四，他们入市政厅去了
- OK, I'm on my way. - Out of the way!
我来了 快让开 !
They're headed for the breezeway on the north side.
他们往信道走去了
I'll be right there.
我马上过去
Hey, Gates!
盖冀1
Enough, man! Give me the document.
够了 ! 把文件给我
All right, Phil.
好吧
Watch out! Get out of my way!
贷了他们，让他们走吧
Watch it!
小心
Leave them! Let 'em go.
让他们走，放了他们
We've got it.
东西到手了
- FBI. Have you seen this guy? - No.
调查局，你看过这个人吗 ? 没有
Nope, I haven't seen him.
没看过他
Ted. Philadelphia police found Gates's car.
警方找到盖冀的车了
It's close. We got surveillance there now.
监控小组已经到场
Let's go. Tell the boss we got the car.
走吧 告诉老板我们找到车了
- What? - We lost it.
怎么? 我们失手了
- We lost the Declaration. lan took it.
什么 ? 独立宣言，伊恩拿走了
Yeah, OK. You all right? You both all right?
你们还好吧 ? 你们都没事吧 ?
Yeah, yeah, we're all right.
我们很好
- Ben, I'm sorry. - We'll be fine.
班，对不起 不会有事的
Meet me at the car.
到车上等我
Suspect has arrived.
嫌犯来了
Hello, Mr. Gates. a
你好，盖益先生
Mr. Gates, face your father's car and put your hands behind your back, please.
请面向车，双手放在身后
- We got one in custody. - Gates, you're a hard man to find.
还捕一人 你还真难找啊
Could you please be careful?
请小心点
Riley, do you know how to get in touch with lan?
莱利，你知道怎么联络伊恩吗 ?
Excuse me?
你说什么 ?
That's some story.
这故事真猛
Well, it's the same story I tried to tell you guys before the Declaration was stolen.
独立宣言被偷前我就告诉你们了
- By you. - No, by lan. I stole it to stop him.
被你偷走 不，被伊恩偷走
I did it alone. Dr. Chase was not involved.
我偷是为了阻止他 是我独自干的，却斯博士不知情
And lan still ended up with the Declaration of Independence.
而伊恩还是拿走了独立宣言
Because of you.
因为你的侨系
So here's your options.
好吧，你有以下的选择
Door number one. a you go to prison for a very long time.
第一道门 你要坐很久很久的牢
Door number two, we are going to get back the Declaration of Independence,
第二道门 我们拿回独立宣言
you help us find it, and you still go to prison for a very long time,
日你帮我们找回它 你还是得坐很久的牢
but you feel better inside.
但你心里会好过一点
Is there a door that doesn't lead to prison?
有没有不用坐宰的门?
- Someone's got to go to prison, Ben. - Yeah.
总有人要去坐牢的 对
So what are these for?
这是用来做什么的?
It's a way to read the map.
用来看地图
Right.
对
Knights Templar.
是哦，圣毁骑士团
Freemasons.
共济会
Invisible treasure map.
隐形藏宝图
- So what'd it say? - "Heere at the wall.”
上面写些什么? "就在墙这几"
Nothing else.
没别的了
It's just another clue.
又是另一条线索
It looks like lan Howe could be a false identity.
伊恩之威可能是个假名
Follow up with ATF and INS.
向移民归化局等相估单位查询
There's more to it.
原来还有东西
- Standard tap procedure. - Let's check the signal, folks.
标准监听程订 人锁定频道
- Checking source. - Unknown number.
寻找发话地点 号码不明
Yes.
好吧
Hello, Ben. How are you?
班，你好吗 ?
- Um. chained to a desk. a - Sorry to hear that.
被错在桌淮 真遗憾啊
I want you to meet me on the flight deck of the USS Intrepid.
我要你到"无刁号"上中我碰面
Meet me there at ten o'clock tomorrow morning.
明早十点
And bring those glasses you found at Independence Hall.
把你找到的那副眼镜也带来
Yeah, Know about the glasses.
没错，我知道眼镜的事了
We can take a look at the Declaration. a and then you can be on your way.
我们先看看独立宣言，再放你走
And I'm supposed to believe that.
我任什么相信你?
I told you from the start, l only wanted to borrow it.
我一直都说我只想借来看看
You can have it. And the glasses.
你可以拿走它，还有了眼镜
I'll even throw in the pipe from the Charlotte.
再加上夏绿蒂号上找到的烟斗
I'll be there.
我会到的
And tell the FBI agents listening in on this call
告诉那些偷听的调查局探员
if they want the Declaration back, and not just a box of confetti,
要是他们想拿回独立宣言 而不是一盒碎纸
then you'll come alone.
就让你一个人单独过来
- Take positions. - Perimeter looks normal.
各就各位 外国看来很正常
- Can l get a status report? - Crow's nest in position. Port side is quiet.
状况报告 港口很平静
Copy that.
知道了
- Gates is on the flight deck. - Eyes on Gates.
盖兹上了甲板 盯着盖冀
- Do not lose sight of primary mark. - Brian, you're clear with NYPD.
别跟去了主要目标 布莱恩，组约警方会配合你
- [have a visual. - Gates.
我这儿目视清楚 盖兹，照计画来
l hope your agents are all uncer four feet tall and wearing little scarves.
希望你的探员是打领由的小孩
Otherwise lan's gonna know they're here.
不然他就会知道有人了盯梢
As soon as he shows you the Declaration, we'll move in.
他一拿出独立宣言，我们就上
Don't try anything. Just let us handle it.
一切交给我们来处理
You know, Agent Sadusky, something I've noticed about fishing:
探员，我认为钓鱼有个问题
it never works out so well for the bait.
不管怎样鱼饵都是受害者
Sir, we've got some traffic incoming. Looks like a sightseeing helicopter.
长官，有直升机飞过来 看来是观光直升机
Unit two. a get an eyeball on that chopper.
注意那台直升机
Agent Michaels, get FAA flight plans and authorization records on that craft.
查明它的飞行计画和授权
If that's not Mr. Howe. a l want to know who it is.
我要知道那上面坐的是谁
- L got him. He’s coming from the north. - Gates. Are you with me?
我看到他了，他从北边过来 盖益，你会跟我合作吧 ?
Well, I'm sure not against you, if that's what you're asking.
我不会跟你作对的
We've got some interference on Gates's mike, sir. a
盖益的麦克风有和干扰
This I know.
我知道
Hello, Ben. a
你好，班
Thomas Edison needed only one way to make a light bulb.
爱迪生只需要一个方法做灯泡
Sound familiar?
这名话很熟吧 ?
- Keep sightlines clear. - What's the devil's going on?
赶快注意目标 这是怎么回事?
There's a lot of commotion. We can't see Gates.
骚动过大 无法看到盖兹
Go to the starboard observation point behind the F-16 and here's what you do.
去右航的观赏台，在F-16后面 照着指示去做
Gates? Gates?
盖兹?
Air Tour helicopter, you are in controlled airspace.
直升机 你超越了限制范国
Vacate immediately.
马上离开
Who's got Gates?
谁看得到盖兹 ?
- All agents, report in. - l can't see anything.
所有探员，快回报 什么都看不到
- Did Gates speak to anybody? - Target is moving.
盖益有跟任何人说话吗 ? 目标移动
- He's heading towarcls the stern. - I've got him. He's coming this way.
他往船尾去了 他往这边来了
Anyone got a view of our friend lan Howe?
有人看到伊恩吗 ?
lan Howe is not at the stern. sir. a
没有，他不在船尾
Then why is he heading there?
他为什么去那儿 ?
He's at the observation deck.
他在观赏甲板上
Sadusky.
沙斯基
I'm still not against you.
我仍然不想跟你作对
But I found door number three. And I'm taking it.
但我找到第三道门了 我打算选它
- What's he talking about? - Move in!
那是什么意思 ? 快过去 !
Divers are a go.
潜水员，快去
- Snipers, go to action zebra. - All teams, move in. Pursue at own risk. a
狙击手，开始Z行动 探员各自负责追捕
- lrepeat, pursue at own risk. - You first.
重复，探员各自负责追捕 你先
Holy mackerel. He set us up.
老天，他设计了我们
Agent Dawes, do you have a visual? Can you see Gates in the water?
看得到盖益在水里吗 ?
Sir, it's the Hudson. Nothing is visible.
这是哈德逊河，水脏的看不清楚
Smart fish.
真聪明的鱼
Hello, Ben. Welcome to New Jersey.
你好，班 欢迎来到纽泽西
- What'd you do with Abigail and Riley? - Hope these fit.
雅析和莱利人呢? 希望合身
We had to guess your sizes.
我们只能猜你的尺寸
I said, what'd you do with Abigail and Riley?
雅析和莱利人呢?
He's the only one who could've told you that line about Edison.
只有他才听过我说 爱迪生的那句话
Did you bring the glasses?
眼镜带来了 ?
I don't know. Tell me what's happening here.
我不知道，怎么回事 ?
Ask your girlfriend.
问你女朋友吧
She's the one calling all the shots now.
一切全是她的主总
She won't shut up.
她就是不肯闭踢
Yeah. hello. a
咀，你好
It's for you.
找你的
- Hello. - Hi, sweetie. How's your day going?
甜心 你今天过的如何 ?
Uh, interesting, dear.
很有趣，亲爱的
So, what, you working with lan now?
你跟伊恩合作了 ?
It turns out helping someone escape from FBI custody is a criminal act.
协助他人逃离调查局监控是犯罪
And he's the only criminal we knew.
他是我们唯一认识的罪犯
- So we called him and made a deal. - Well, you're...
我们打电话给他，跟他达成交易 那你…
You're... you're... you're all right, yeah? I mean you're safe?
你还好吧 ?你安全吗 ?
Yeah. we both are. a
我们都很好
Riley's right here, doing something clever with a computer.
莱利正在用计算机做很聪明的事
I'm tracking him through the... Hey!
我正在追踪你…
I'm tracking you through the GPS in Shaw's phone.
透过老莆手机的卫星定位
They take a turn anywhere we don't want, we'll know it. So don't worry.
若他们乱跑，我们会知道
If lan tries to double-cross us. we can call a the FBI and tell them right where you are.
伊恩若想要赖，我们就找调查局
- And where to find lan. - And where is that?
告诉他们你和伊息人在哪儿 那会是哪儿呢?
Right across the street from where we're hiding,
就在我们对街
at the intersection of Wall Street and Broadway.
华尔街和百老汇街的转角
Well, you figured out the clue.
你理清楚那个线索了
Simple. "Heere at the wall.” Wall Street and Broadway.
简单，华尔街和百老汇街转角
Ben, there is a catch. a
班，有个问题
We made lan believe he could have the treasure.
我们让伊恩相信他能拥有宝藏
It was the only way we could get this far.
那是唯一的办法
He's here.
他到了
Here we go.
开始了
Ben.
班
You all right? No broken bones? A jump like that could kill a man.
你没事吧 ? 没受伤 ? 那样跳下来会要人命的
The Declaration of Independence. And the meerschaum pipe.
独立宣言 海泡石烟斗
All yours.
全是你的了
- That's it? - That's it.
就这样 ? 就这样
I knew you'd keep your promise. Now, where is it? Where's my treasure?
我知道你会信守承诺的 我的宝藏哗?
It's right here.
就在这几
The map said "Heere at the wall.” spelled with two E's.
地图上写 "就在墙这儿(Heere)"
Wall Street follows the path of an actual wall
华尔街以前刚好是一道墙
that the original Dutch settlers built as a defense to keep the British out.
是荷兰移民建来抵御英国人的
The main gate was located at a street called De Heere. also two E's. a
正门座落的那条街就叫"Heere"
Later De Heere Street was renamed Broadway after the British got in.
后来这街被英国人改名为百老汇
So. "Heere at the wall.” a
"就在墙这儿(Heere)"
Broadway, Wall Street.
就是指百老汇和华尔街
Cheerio.
再见 !
Just a moment. Ben. a
等一等
lan, if you break our deal, the FBI will be only a few minutes behind you.
伊恩，违反承诺 调查局就会找上你
You might get away, you might not.
你也许能逃脱，也许不能
Is that all the map said?
地图上就说这些 ?
Every word.
一字不漏
Oh, Ben. a
班…
You know the key to running a convincing bluff?
你知道距人成功的侨键何在 ?
Every once in a while you've got to be holding all the cards.
每了一阵子 你手上就得握有所有王牌
Dad.
区
Is there anything else you want to tell me?
你还有什么想告诉我的?
Trinity Church. We have to go inside Trinity Church.
三一教堂 进三一教堂
Good. Excellent.
好，很好
Well, why don't you ask Dr. Chase and Riley to join us?
叫却斯博士跟莱利加入我们吧
I'm sure they're around here somewhere.
我相信他们就在附近
Are you all right?
你还好吧 ?
What clo you think? I'm a hostage.
你以为呢?我是人质耶
Sit. Sit down.
坐下
- Let him go, lan. - When we find the treasure.
放他走，伊恩 找到宝藏就放
No, now. Or you can figure out the clues for yourself.
不行，就是现在 那你自己解恋吧
Good luck.
祝你好运
Ben.
班
I don't think you fully appreciate the gravity of the situation.
我不认为你明白情况有多严重
Let's have a look at that map.
我们一起看地图吧
It's... it's really quite something. It's...
不得了…
It really is remarkable. Take a look.
真的很了不起，你看
- "Parkington Lane.” - "Beneath Parkington Lane.”
帕金顿起 怕金上顿夫下面
But why would the map lead us here, then take us somewhere else?
为何地图引我们来此 又叫我们去别处?
- What's the purpose? - Just another clue.
这是什么用意 ? 只是另一个线索黑了
Dad. No, you're right. Parkington Lane has to be here somewhere.
区 怕金上顿埠一定就在这儿某处
A street inside the church?
教堂里有一条巷子 ?
Not inside. Beneath.
不是在里边，是在下面
Beneath the church.
在教堂下面
- I'm so sorry, Ben. - None of this is your fault.
很对不起，班 这不是你的错
- Ico... - Come on.
我 走吧
Look.
听着
Cooperation only lasts as long as the status quo is unchanged.
只有保持现状才能继续合作
As soon as this guy gets to wherever this thing ends, he won't need you anymore.
一旦行动结束 他就不需要你
Or... or any of us.
或我们了
So we find a way to make sure the status quo changes in our favor.
我们得让情况转而对咱们有利
- How? - I'm still working on it.
怎么做 ? 我正在想
Well. I guess I better work on it too, then. a
那我想我也最好想一想了
Hey! Par... Hey, I found it!
我找到了 !
- Him! - Ben!
是他 ! 班
It's a name.
这是个名字
Parkington Lane.
狐金顿雷恩
He was a third-degree master mason of the Blue Lo...
他是共济会第三级会员…
Hey! Stop!
站住
Easy.
小心
Careful no one steps in him.
小必别踩到他
All right, put it down.
放下
OK. Who wants to go down the creepy tunnel insicle the tomb first?
谁想先踏进恐怖的坟墓信道 ?
Right. McGregor, Viktor, you stay here.
好 麦格、维多，你们留在这
And if anyone should come out without me, well... use your imagination.
要是没有我带着却有人出来 运用你们的想象力吧
Shall we?
可以走了吧?
You got a light?
有火吗?
Careful.
小心
Watch your step.
注意脚步
Why does that never happen to me?
为什么我就碰不上这种好事 ?
What's this?
这是什么 ?
It's a chandelier.
是个大吊灯
Here.
这几
- Wow. - Look at the elevators.
哇 看看那些升降梯
A dumbwaiter system.
传送食物用的升降梯
How do a bunch of guys with hand tools build all this?
这些人是怎么徒手建造这些的 ?
Same way they built the pyramids and the Great Wall of China.
跟埃及人金字塔和中国长城一样
Yeah. The aliens helped them.
是啊，外星人帮他们造的
Right, let's go. What are we waiting for?
是哦，走吧
I'm not going out on that thing. 200 years of termite damage and rot.
我才不走这按呢 经过了200年的虫星腐朽
Dad, do what he says.
和区，照他说的话去做
Watch your step.
小心脚步
We're right uncer the Trinity graveyard.
我们在三一教堂的墓地下面
That's probably why no one ever found this.
难怪没人发现这几
What is that?
那是什么 ?
Subway.
地铁
Shaw! Oh. God. Shaw! ee
天哪
Oh, my God.
我的老天
Hold on! Hold on!
抓住 !
OK, get on the elevator. Jump!
上升降梯，快跳 !
Ben! Grab my hand.
班 ! 抓住我的手
- Come on. - lan!
上来 ! 伊恩
Abigail! Get on!
雅珀，快上去 !
Jump!
快跳!
Here.
这几
Ben!
班 !
Get down there. Get down there!
下去那儿 !
The Declaration.
独立宣言
- Do you trust me? - Yes.
你信任我吗 ? 信任
Oh, no! Ben! a
不，班!
Hang on!
抓紧 !
Son!
儿子 !
I'm sorry. I'm sorry I dropped you. l had to save the Declaration.
抱数和去下你，我得救回独立宣言
No, don't be. I would have done a exactly the same thing to you.
不用道莱，我也会做同样的抉择
Really?
真的?
I would have dropped you both. Freaks.
我会把你们两个全都丢下去 怪脸
Get on.
上来
lan...
伊恩
it's not worth it.
这不值得的
Do you imagine any one of your lives is more valuable to me than Shaw's?
你以为你们任何人的命 对我而言会比老莆重要吗 ?
We go on.
继续前进
The status quo. Keep the status quo.
保持现状
- Now what? - This is...
现在呢?
This is where it all leads.
一切线索都指向这儿
OK, let's go.
走吧
What is this?
这是什么 ?
So where's the treasure?
宝藏在哪?
Well?
怎样 ?
This is it?
就这样 ?
We came all this way for a dead end?
历尽艰辛找到的却是死胡同 ?
Yes.
是的
- There's gotta be something more. - Riley, there's nothing more.
一定还有什么东西 没有了
- Another clue, or... a - No. there are no more clues!
另一个线索 不，没有线索了
That's it. OK? It's over! a
就是这样，好吗 ?
End of the road. The treasure’s gone. Moved. Taken somewhere else.
宝藏不见了 ! 被搬走 ! 移到别的地方了
You're not playing games with me, are you, Ben? Hm?
你不是在要我吧?
You know where it is.
你知道宝藏在哪
No.
不
OK, go.
好，走吧
Hey, wait a minute.
等一等
- Hey! lan, wait! - Wait. wait. wait! a
伊恩，等等 ! 等等 ! 等一下
- lan... - We'll be trapped.
伊恩 我们会被困住的 !
- Don't do this. - You can't just leave us here.
别这样 ! 你不能把我们丢在这
Yes. l can. a Unless Ben tells me the next clue.
我能，除非班告诉我下一条线索
There isn't another clue.
没有别的线索了
lan, why don't you come back down here and we can talk through this together?
伊四，快回来啊 咱们好好谈一谈
- Don't speak again. - OK.
给我闭踢 好吧
The clue. Where's the treasure?
宝藏在哪?
Ben?
班
- The lantern. - Dad...
油灯 区
The status quo has changed, son.
现状已经改变
Don't.
别说
It's part of freemason teachings.
共济会的会训里有罕
In King Solomon's temple there was a winding staircase.
所罗门王圣攻有座跪购的楼梯
It signified the journey that had to be made to find the light of truth.
象征必须完成的旅途 以寻找真理的明灯
- The lantern is the clue. - And what does it mean?
油灯就是线索 那代表什么意思?
Boston. It's Boston.
波士上，那是指波士顿
The Old North Church in Boston. a
旭北教堂
where Thomas Newton hung a lantern in the steeple,
汤玛士纽顿在那儿挂上油灯
to signal Paul Revere that the British were coming. One if by land, two if by sea.
以警告保罗里维尔英人来克 昌陆路来挂一乞，海路则挂两必
One lantern. Under the winding staircase of the steeple, that’s where we have to look.
哎嗓的楼梯下挂了一乞灯，你看
- Thank you. - Hey, you have to take us with you.
谢了 你得带我们一起去
Why? So you can escape in Boston?
为什么 ? 好证你们借机和逃跑?
Besides, with you out of the picture there's less baggage to carry.
没了你们，我的负担也比较轻
What if we lied?
要是我们骗你呢 ?
Did you?
你骗了我吗?
What if there's another clue?
要是还有别的线索呢 ?
Then I'll know right where to find you.
那我知道该到哪找你
See you, Ben.
再见了，班
- No! - There's no other way out!
不! 没有别的路能出去了 !
- Come back! - You're gonna need us, lan!
回来 你会需要我们的!
We're all gonna die.
我们会死的
It's gonna be OK, Riley. I'm sorry I yelled at you.
不会有事的，莱利 抱娄我对你乱吼
It's OK. kiddo. a
没事的，孩子
OK, boys, what's going on? The British came by sea. It was two lanterns, not one.
好了，这是怎么回事?
lan needed another clue. a so we gave it to him.
伊恩要线索，我们就给他线索
It was a fake. It was a fake clue.
那是假的，假线索 !
The all-seeing eye.
全知之眼
"Through the all-seeing eye.”
透过全知之限
That means... by the time lan figures it out and comes back here,
等伊恩型明白的时候
we'll still be trapped, and he'll shoot us then.
他会回来，而我们还被困在这 到时他会杀了咱们
Either way, we're gonna die.
不管怎样咱们都死定了
Nobody's gonna die. There's another way out.
没有人会死，有出去的路
Where?
在哪?
Through the treasure room.
经由藏宝室
Here.
这几
Riley.
莱利
Looks like someone got here first.
看起来…有人先到过这儿了
I'm sorry, Ben.
对不起，班
It's gone.
全被搬空了
- Listen. Ben... a - It may have even been gone
听着，儿子 在卡洛告诉汤玛斯盖认这故事前
before Charles Carroll told the story to Thomas Gates.
宝藏可能就被搬走了
It doesn't matter.
没人关系了
I know. 'Cause you were right.
我知道，因为你是对的
No, I wasn't right.
不，我不是
This room is real, Ben. a
这房间是真的
And that means the treasure is real.
那代表宝藏也是真的
We're in the company of some of the most brilliant minds in history,
我们与史上最聪明的人并驾齐驱
because you found what they left behind for us to find
多亏你找出他们留下的宝藏
and understood the meaning of it.
以及这宝藏的意义
You did it, Ben. For all of us. a
你做到了，为了我们
Your grandfather, and all of us.
为你区务，还有咱们
And I've never been so happy to be proven wrong.
我很高兴你能证明我错了
I just...
只是…
really thought Il was gonna find the treasure.
我真以为我能找到宝藏
OK.
好吧
Then we just keep looking for it.
那咱们就继续寻找宝藏
I'm in.
算我一份
OK.
好吧
Not to be Johnny Rain Cloud here, but that's not gonna happen.
我不想让大人炙扫兴，不过那不可能
Because as far as I can see. a we're still trapped down here.
在我看来，我们还困在这几
Yeah.
是呀
Now, Ben, oe where is this other way out?
另一条出去的路呢?
Well. that's it. a It doesn't make any sense,
这没道理，建造这儿的人
because the first thing the builders would have done after getting down here
一定会先建造第二换气坑
was cut a secondary shaft back out for air...
以防发生塌的状况
- Right. - ..and in case of cave-ins.
对 万一发生拥珊
Could it really be that simple?
不会真的这么简单吧 ?
"The secret lies with Charlotte.”
"秘密与夏绿蒂同在"
Scrolls from the library at Alexandria.
亚历山大图书馆的滚动条
Could this be possible?
这可能吗?
It's a big... bluish-green man,
这个高大的蓝绿色男人
with a strange-looking goatee.
还留着可笑的山羊胡
I'm guessing that's significant.
我想那应该很有意义吧
Yes!
好耶
Riley, are you crying?
莱利，你在哭吗?
Look.
快看
Stairs.
有楼梯
Hi.
你好
Do you have a cell phone I could borrow?
能不能借用一下你的手机?
- Just like that? - Just like that.
就这样 ? 就这样
You do know you just handed me your biggest bargaining chip?
你刚刚交出了你最大的筹码
The Declaration of Independence is not a bargaining chip.
独立宣言不是筹码
Not to me.
对我而言不是
Have a seat.
坐吧
So what's your offer?
你有人和何条件 ?
How about a bribe? Say...
我提个贿赂吧 ?
ten billion dollars?
就开价…一千亿?
I take it you found the treasure?
你找到宝藏了
It's about five stories beneath your shoes.
就在你脚下五层楼深的地底
You know, the Templars and the Freemasons believed
骑士们和共济会员都相信
that the treasure was too great for any one man to have, not even a king.
这伟大的宝藏不该为人所有 就连帝王也一样
That's why they went to such lengths to keep it hidden.
此他们才会设法埋藏宝藏
That's right.
没错
The Founding Fathers believed the same thing about government.
建国先贤对政府也有相同的想法
I figure their solution will work for the treasure too.
他们的解答也适用于宝藏
Give it to the people.
一切为全民所有
Divide it amongst the Smithsonian, the Louvre. the Cairo museum... a
将宝藏分送世界各大博物馆
There's thousands of years of world history down there.
这其中包含数千年的世界历史
And it belongs to the world, and everybody in it.
它属于全世界，以及所有人
You really don't understand the concept of a bargaining chip.
你还真不会运用筹码
OK, here's what I want. a Dr. Chase gets off completely clean,
我的条件是…却斯博士全身而退
hot even a little Post-it on her service record.
她档案里不能有任何加注
OK.
好
I want the credit for the find to go to the entire Gates family,
我要将一切荣洒汶于盖兹家族
with the assistance of Mr. Riley Poole.
以及莱和波尔先生的大力协助
And what about you?
你呢 ?
I'd really love not to go to prison.
我很希望不要坐牢
I can't even begin to describe how much I would love not to go to prison.
我不知道该怎么形容我的渴望
Someone's got to go to prison, Ben.
总有人要去坐牢的
Well, if you've got a helicopter, I think I can help with that.
若你有直升机，我就能帮你搞定
Freeze! FBI!
不准动
- Freeze! Don't move! - Show me your hands!
站住，不准动 ! 举起双手
- Put your hands up. - Move, move, move. a
双手举高 走，快走
You're under arrest. Mr. Howe.
你被捕了，裳威先生
We've got you on kidnapping, attempted murder...
你涉嫌绑架、杀人未遂…
and trespassing on government property.
非法入侵国有财产
Yeah. You got it, chief. Thank you. Bye.
没错，谢啦，拜
They want us in Cairo next week for the opening of the exhibit.
他们要咱们去开罗参加展览开幕
They're sending a private jet.
他们会派私人喷射机来
That's fun.
真好玩
Yeah, big whoop. We could have had a whole fleet of private jets.
才怪，咱们本来能有喷射机队的
Ten percent, Ben. They offered you ten percent and you turned it down.
百分之十，班 他们要给你10%，你却不要
Riley, we've been over this. It was too much. I couldn't accept it.
那太多了，我不能接人受
I still have this splinter that's been festering for three months from an old piece of wood.
我合的只不过是沧海一村
OK, I'll tell you what.
好，告诉你
Next time we find a treasure that redefines history for all mankind,
下回再找到惊天动地的宝藏
you make the call on the finder's fee.
寻宝费就由你来开
That's not as funny.
那一点也不好玩
What clo you care? You got the girl.
你反正不在平，你找到了真爱
- It's true.
那倒是
Rub it in. Enjoy your spoils...
真过分，你们慢慢玩吧
while I sit on one percent.
我则要享受这百分之一
One stinkin’ percent. Half of one percent, actually.
其实也只有百分之零点五
One percent. Unbelievable.
才拿百分之一，真不可思议
I'm sorry for your suffering, Riley.
抱娄让你这么难过
For the record, Ben, oe l like the house.
说真的，我喜欢这标羽子
You know. I chose this estate a because in 1812 Charles Carroll met...
1812年，罕尔斯卡洛在此…
Yeah, someone that did something in history and had fun. Great. Wonderful.
见了茶人或做了茶件大事 你很厉害、你很强
Could have had a bigger house.
你本来可以买更大的房子的
- [made something for you. - You did? What?
我做了个东西给你 是吗?是什么?
-Amap. -A map?
一幅地图 地图?
Where cles it lead to?
做什么用的?
You'll figure it out.
你会找到解答的